Paul-Henry Leemann

Researcher in Pure Mathematics

Université de Neuchâtel Institut de mathématiques 2000 Neuchâtel, Suisse ⊠ Paul-Henry.Leemann@unine.ch '`` www.leemann.website



Personal Information

Date of Birth April 12, 1987 Citizenship Switzerland

Main areas of research

My research interests lie in the intersection of geometric and combinatorial group theory, graph theory and symbolic dynamic. I am particularly interested in groups acting on rooted trees and their (weakly) maximal subgroups, limits and coverings of (Schreier) graphs, rigidity phenomenon in Cayley and Schreier graphs and graphs associated to dynamical systems.

Employment

Starting Xi'an Jiaotong-Liverpool University, Suzhou, China, Assistant Professor, in February 2022 Department of Pure Mathematics.

Since **Université de Neuchâtel, Switzerland**, Scientific collaborator, in Institut de September 2021 mathématiques.

2020-2021 **Université de Neuchâtel, Switzerland**, *Post-Doc*, in Institut de mathématiques, with Alain Valette.

2018–2020 **ENS-Lyon, France**, *Post-Doc*, in Unité de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, with Mikael de la Salle.

Post-Doc Labex MILYON

2016–2018 **ENS-Lyon, France**, *Post-Doc*, in Unité de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, with Mikael de la Salle.

Early Postdoc. Mobility grant supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation

Education

2011–2016 **Université de Genève, Switzerland**, *Ph.D. in Mathematics*, "On Subgroups and Schreier Graphs of Finitely Generated Groups", advisor: Tatiana Smirnova-Nagnibeda.

Mention très bien

2013–2015 Université de Genève, Switzerland, Basic Certificate of Didactic in Mathematics and in Educational Science.

2009–2011 Université de Genève, Switzerland, M. Sc. in Mathematics, Master-thesis: "Caractères irréductibles des groupes de Coxeter finis", advisors: Pierre de la Harpe and Tatiana Smirnova-Nagnibeda.

grades: 6/6 (Master-thesis) and 5.7/6 (courses)

2006–2009 Université de Genève, Switzerland, B. Sc. in Mathematics.

Publications

- 1. Property FW and wreath products of groups: a simple approach using Schreier graphs, with G. Schneeberger. Accepted in Expositiones Mathematicae (2021). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.03817
- 2. Cayley graphs with few automorphisms: the case of infinite groups, with M. de la Salle. To appear in Annales Henri Lebesgue (2021). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.06020
- 3. Up to a double cover, every regular connected graph is isomorphic to a Schreier graph. To appear in Bulletin of the Belgian Mathematical Society Simon Stevin Vol. 28 issue 4 (2021). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.06431
- 4. Finitely generated subgroups of branch groups and subdirect products of just infinite groups, with R. Grigorchuk and T. Nagnibeda. Izvestia: Math. Vol. 85 (2021) https://doi.org/10.1070/IM9101
- 5. Cayley graphs with few automorphisms, with M. de la Salle. J Algebr Comb (2020). https://doi.org/10.1007/s10801-020-00956-1
- 6. Schreier graphs: Transitivity and Coverings. Internat. J. Algebra Comput., Vol. 26, Issue 1 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1142/S021819671650003X
- 7. Weakly maximal subgroups in regular branch groups, with K. Bou-Rabee and T. Nagnibeda. Journal of Algebra, Vol. 455 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jalgebra.2016.02.009
- 8. Lamplighter groups, de Bruijn graphs, spider-web graphs and their spectra, with R. Grigorchuk and T. Nagnibeda. Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical, Vol. 49, Number 20 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1088/1751-8113/49/20/205004

Preprints

- 1. Most rigid representation and Cayley index of finitely generated groups, With M. de la Salle. (2021). https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.02326
- 2. Wreath products of groups acting with bounded orbits, with G. Schneeberger. (2021). https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.08001
- 3. Subgroup induction property for branch groups, with D. Francoeur. (2020). https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.13310
- 4. Weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups. (2020). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.06399

Prizes, Grants and Scientific Visits

- 2021-2022 "Group theory, topology and dynamics: Russian-Swiss collaboration", 2 years collaboration
 - 2016 Vacheron Constantin prize for the best thesis in mathematics, *Université de Genève*, Switzerland
- 07-12 2015 Semester "Analytic and Geometric Aspects of Probability on Graphs", EPFL, Switzer-land
- 01-04 2014 IHP Semester "Marches aléatoires et géométrie asymptotique des groupes", CIRM and IHP, France
- April 2011 Topology and Geometric Group Theory, Columbus, Ohio, USA

Conferences organisation

- June 2022 "Groups Acting on Fractals" Thematic Trimester, conference organizer, 30 May-3 June, Institut Henri Poincaré, France
- May 2021 Kervaire seminar "Baum-Connes conjecture", co-organizer, 23-28 May, Les Diablerets, Switzerland
- March 2013 Kervaire seminar "Géométrie des groupes 2013", co-organizer, 10-15 March, Les Diablerets, Switzerland

Talks (selected)

Conferences:

- August 2021 World Of Group Craft, inline conference, Wreath product of groups acting with bounded orbits.
 - June 2018 Trees Dynamics and Locally Compact Groups, Heinrich Heine University, Dusseldörf, Germany. Profinite completion of weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups.
- January 2017 Rencontre GAMME, Sète, France. Weakly maximal subgroups of the Grigorchuk group. Existence and construction of IRS.
- November 2014 Paroles aux jeunes chercheurs en géométrie et dynamique, GDR Platon, Université de Bordeaux, France. A criterion for the transitivity of Schreier graphs.
 - June 2014 Workshop in Algebra and Geometry, University of Bern, Switzerland. Transitivity of Schreier graphs and strongly simple groups.
- September 2013 Geometric and Analytic Group Theory, Ventotene, Italy. Transitivity of Schreier graphs.

Seminars:

- May 2021 Séminaire Groupes et Géométrie, Université de Genève, Switzerland. Produit en couronne et groupes agissant avec des orbites bornées.
- April 2021 Algebra Seminar, Lincoln University, United-Kingdom. Branch groups and the subgroup induction property. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/subgroupinduction.pdf
- April 2021 Séminaire Géométrie, Algèbre, Algèbre d'opérateurs, Université de Clermont-Ferrand, France. Graphes de Cayley avec peu d'automorphismes. Slides (in French): http://www.leemann.website/slides/clermont-ferrand.pdf
- March 2021 Group theory seminar, ENS, Paris, France. De Bruijn graphs, spider web graphs and Lamplighter groups. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/bruijn.pdf
- February 2021 Symmetry in Newcastle, University of Newcastle, Australia. Rigidity of Cayley graphs. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/newcastle.pdf
- November 2020 Colloque du département de mathématiques, Université de Neuchâtel, Switzerland.

 Groups and graphs: rigidity phenomena. Slides (in French): http://www.leemann.

 website/slides/rigidity.pdf
 - March 2020 Séminaire Groupes et Géométrie, Université de Genève, Switzerland. Weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/weaklymaximal.pdf
 - October 2019 Séminaire de Géométrie, Groupes et Dynamiques, ENS Lyon. Rigidity of Cayley graphs.
 - July 2019 Séminaire Darboux, Montpellier, France. Rigidity of Cayley graphs.

Teaching Experiences

2020–2021 In Neuchâtel:

- "Branch groups", a 6 hours mini-course for doctoral students

2016–2020 In ENS Lyon:

- Teaching assistant of "Coverings and fundamental groups" (master)
- Teacher of "Introduction to LATEX" (3rd year class)

2011–2016 Teaching assistant at the University of Genève:

- Advanced course on Combinatorics (master)
- Algebra II: groups, rings, fields, Galois theory (2nd year class)
- Algebra I: linear algebra (1st year class)
- Analysis I: basics of logic and set theory, real analysis (1st year class)
- General mathematics: 1st year class for students of other departments
- Tutoring for first year students

2006–2011 Private tutor in mathematics for high school students

Refereeing

I have been a referee for the following journals: Journal of Algebra, International Journal of Algebra and Computation, L'enseignement mathématiques, Expositiones Mathematicae, Journal of Algebra and its Applications.

Scientific popularization

- 2017 MATH α LYON: interactive workshop in Junior High School, Lyon, France
- 2014-2016 Mentor in the "boussole" curriculum (one week of immersion in the mathematics' department, for High School's students), Genève, Switzerland
- 2012-2016 Facilitator at the University "Open Day", Genève, Switzerland
- 2011-2016 Mathematics' facilitator in Junior High School and High School classes, Genève, Switzerland
 - 2015 Facilitator at the "Science's night", Genève, Switzerland

Languages

French: native English: fluent German: basics

Others

Computer skills (LA)TFX (advanced), HTML/CSS and GAP (basics)

Recommandation letters

The following people have letters of recommendation available: Rostislav Grigorchuk (distinguished Professor A&M University Texas, grigorch@math.tamu.edu), Tatiana Nagnibeda (associate professor Geneva Switzerland, Tatiana.Smirnova-Nagnibeda@unige.ch), Mikael de la Salle (assistant professor ENS Lyon France, mikael.de.la.salle@ens-lyon.fr) and Alain Valette (full professor Neuchâtel Switzerland, alain.valette@unine.ch).